Guide to the Thomas Goddard Bergin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Subject Files and Photographs, 1952-1971; Series III
  The first section, which relates to the celebration of the Dante septicentennial, consists of correspondence and other documentation bearing upon Yale's commemoration of the 700th anniversary of Dante's birth in October, 1965. The materials in this section document Bergin's organization of a conference as Yale's tribute to Dante. Bergin attempted to ensure that Yale's Dante scholars featured prominently at the conference. He was only partly successful since several Yale faculty members declined Bergin's offer to lecture. There is correspondence and both draft and final versions of the lectures originally delivered October 4-20 at Yale by Kenelm Foster, Thomas Greene, Raffaello Morghen, Giorgio Petrocchi, Natalino Sapegno, and Aldo Scaglione. Other material relates to Bergin's efforts to edit and publish the lectures, which eventually appeared as From Time to Eternity: Essays on Dante's Comedy (1967). In this effort he had the support of George Pierson, the chairman of the university's Division of the Humanities, and Yale University Press and its editor, Chester Kerr. Bergin's report for the Division of the Humanities can be found in folder 13, while materials in folder 2 document Bergin's collaboration with Vincenzo Cioffari, the national chairman of the Dante Centenary Committee, and Connecticut Representative Robert N. Giamo to prepare a bill commissioning the United States Post Office to issue a commemorative Dante stamp.
  The second section contains files which document Bergin's research in Italian literature throughout most his career. It consists of Bergin's handwritten and typed notes on the works of several prominent Italian writers, such as Alberto Moravia, Niccolò Machiavelli, and Torquato Tasso. Files typically contain chapter summaries and select notes from secondary sources on a particular work of literature, for example Machiavelli's Mandragola.
  The section "Yale University" documents Bergin's administrative roles at Yale, especially his involvement with the Yale Alumni Association, his duties as chairman of the Spanish and Italian Department (1949-1958), Master of Timothy Dwight College (1953-1968), and chairman of the Committee on Area Studies (1950-1953). The bulk of the material in this section dates from the 1950s.
  The last two sections, Personal and Photographs, include correspondence relating to the estate of Bergin's sister, Hortense G. Hanly, who died in Naugatuck, Connecticut, on April 23, 1965 and Christmas cards from friends. There are also a few photographs of Bergin and his acquaintances.
  - Dante septicentennial
    - Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Commemorative stamp, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Documentary film project, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - From Time to Eternity: Essays on Dante's Comedy
      - Foster, Kenelm, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Greene, Thomas M., 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Mack, Maynard, 1963-1964 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Morghen, Raffaello, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Petrocchi, Giorgio, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Pierson, George, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Sapegno, Natalino, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Scaglione, Aldo, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Singleton, Charles, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Taylor, Charles H., 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Yale University Press, 1963-1967 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - New Haven Dante week, 1965 October 10-17 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Schedule of lectures, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Yale University News Bureau, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Italian literature
    - Belli, Giuseppe G., undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Courtly figures, troubadours, Undated (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Crusades, Undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Dante diagrams, Undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Dante's Paradise, Undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Machiavelli, Niccolò, Undated
      - Clizia (Box 12, Folder 24)
      - Discorsi sopra la prima deca di Tito Livio (Box 12, Folder 25)
      - Istorie Fjorentine (Box 12, Folder 26)
      - Mandragola (Box 12, Folder 27)
      - Miscellaneous notes (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Moravia, Alberto, Undated
      - Agostino (Box 12, Folder 29)
      - L 'Amante lnfelice (Box 12, Folder 30)
      - La Bella Vita (Box 12, Folder 31)
      - The Conformist (Box 12, Folder 32)
      - Conjugal Love (Box 12, Folder 33)
      - L'Epidemia (Box 12, Folder 34)
      - Gli Indifferenti (Box 12, Folder 35)
      - La Romana (Box 12, Folder 36)
      - Sogni del Pigro (Box 12, Folder 37)
      - La Speranza (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Romance literature, Undated (Box 12, Folder 39)
    Short bibliographic notes on various Italian writers.
  - Tasso, Torquato [ Gerusalemme Liberata ], Undated (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Translation project, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 41)
    Series of classics of Italian literature in English translation.
  - Verga, Giovanni [notes on Il Malavoglia ], Undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Yale University
    - Alumni Association
      - Board, 1957-1960 (Box 12, Folder 43)
      - Conference, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 44)
      - Seminar, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 45)
      - Trip, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - Committee of Foreign Area Studies, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - Committee on Languages, 1953-1954 (Box 13, Folder 48)
    - Graduate Affiliates Program, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 49)
    - Leopardi, Giacomo [seminar class], 1970 (Box 13, Folder 50)
    - Spanish and Italian Department and French Department, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 51)
    - Timothy Dwight College, Circa 1953-1968 (Box 13, Folder 52)
    - Miscellaneous, Circa 1953-1966 (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - Personal
    - Christmas cards, Undated (Box 13, Folder 54)
    - Hanly, Hortense [sister's estate], 1962-1966 (Box 13, Folder 55)
  - Photographs
    - Bergin, Thomas, Undated (Box 13, Folder 56)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 13, Folder 57)
- Additional Material, Accession 2012-M-051
  - Letter to Albert D. Putnam with three poems included -- " Age," Staging Area," and "Rime 9" (translation of Petrach), 1974 May 12 (Box 1)